hello guys so in today's video we're
going to talk about Market structure
this particular topic is very important
for you as a Trader you don't just open
the chart and start looking for entries
without understanding the general story
in the market so that is what I'm going
to point out for you in this video how
to read the market structure and point
out levels where you can be taking your
interest from make sure you watch till
the very end to understand how to map
out all the structures Mar out valid
Origins without taking entries from
liquidity zones or enement levels so
guys you know to do let us stly
[Applause]
[Music]
CH so guys before we go into analyzing
the real chart let me quickly give you
guys an illustration of the different
types of Market structure because when
it comes to Market structure we have
three types of Market structure we have
the bullish Trend and um the bearish
trend and then we have that of the
sideways movement or you can call it a
ranging Market or um a consolidating
market or you can just call it
sideways
movement so these are the three types of
Market structure now at the end of this
video I will get to point out the
structure that works more with our
strategy that is smart money concept so
make sure you watch till the very end to
point out how to use these different
Market structure
to your own benefit so pointing out the
bullish
Trend whenever Market is breaking
structure to the upside like
this creating higher highs and higher
lows higher highs like this and higher
lows just have it in mind that that is a
bullish
Trend so you can see the breakout
structure here from here so let me point
it out can see this is the break of
structure this is another break of
structure and
um this is another break of structure so
whenever you open a chart and you see
this type of movement just know that the
market is bullish and then whenever you
open the chart and you notice that the
market is creating you know lower lows
lower high lower lows lower high just
breaking structures to the downside have
it in mind that the market is
bearish so let me clone this here so
it's breaking structure to the downside
have it in mind that the market is
bearish just like this breaking
structure to the downside then for that
of the sideways movement whenever the
market is giving equal highs equal low
equal highs equal low equal highs and
equal low just know that it's a sideways
movement or that the market is r ring
consolidating and so on so these are the
three types of Market structure now if
you read the market structure and you
notice that it is indicating that it is
bullish all you need to be looking out
for is how to buy and then if you read
the market structure and you notice that
it is bearish all you need to be looking
out for is how to sell that particular
commodity then if you read the market
structure and you notice that it has you
know sideways movement ranging
you really need to wait for a breakout
first we're going to go to the Chart now
and we're going to analyze different
currency Pairs and you will see how to
map out Market structures and different
origins or pois where you can take your
entries from so guys looking at the real
chart we're going to read this
particular Market structure that is on
gpp USD from the daily time frame
whenever I'm reading the market
structure or I'm trying to understand
the general story in the market I
normally start from the daily time frame
to understand the general Trend the
general story and from there I will head
straight to my entry time frame so I
believe you should know this if you've
seen the video where I explained um
multi-time frame analysis so guys
looking at
this if you're trying to use your trend
line for trend line Traders once you
place this you'll notice that the price
is pointed to the downside which
indicates a downtrend but that is not
enough for you because if you just place
that you may find it difficult to get
your entries but if you learn how to
read the market structure by mapping out
the origins knowing the origin that
price has mitigated and the rest that
will help you you know to point out your
you know levels in the market and where
you can take entries from so from here
you can see that we've been having break
of structure to the upside so this was
more like the last break of structure to
the upside although it was more of an
internal structure let me it out well a
break of structure to the
upside and now when price got here it
couldn't break further it created equal
high so leaving this level more like um
a resistant level just around this point
here leaving it as a resistant level and
from there price started retracing and
cleared out the last origin which is
this level that caused a break of
structure
so as price cleared out this last origin
remember the market was trending to the
upside from here but when it got here
that was actually a h and from there it
started pushing to the downside clearing
out the last origin that caused a break
of stru to the upside so that means that
a change of character has
happened so that means we have a change
of
character so you can call it church just
like this so we have a change of
character around this level so you can
see after the change of character now
watch this guys because this is actually
how you can map out your origin now
change of character indicates that the
market has changed Trend that is from up
to down or from down to up so from what
we can see here now on the chart price
has actually um changed trend from up to
down because we've gotten a break of
structure to the downside instead of to
the upside so now where is actually the
origin that caused this break of
structure or this change of
character now you can see after this
consolidation everything that happened
here price you know created the
impulsive movement that cleared out the
change of character so from
here this is actually the origin that
caused the change of character and you
can see after price you know cleared out
this level saw how price retraced you
can see it here you can see how price
retraced
into this particular origin and from
there it started breaking more
structures to the downside so now we
have
this we have another break of structure
here to the
downside so let me just be cloning this
drawings so that to be easier for me so
we have another break of structure here
to the downside what happened where is
the origin that caused this particular
of structure guys you can see this is
the origin so I'm just going to m about
everything there so you can see how
price retraced tapped into the origin
that cost this particular break of
structure and what are we getting
further break of structure to the
downside so just like the illustration I
showed you guys earlier so we are
currently looking at a bearish trend
this is how you can see how price is
creating you know lower lows lower
highs now we have another break of
structure where is the origin that
caused this particular break of
structure this is the origin
this is the origin here and what
happened price retrac tapped into it so
now as you're reading this particular
Market structure you know this is just
an example so if you reading this from a
real time chart that is when the market
is moving because currently the market
is closed when the market is moving if
you get all the things once to point out
a break of structure if price should get
back into the origin that cost it look
for sale sell another break of structure
you look for sale that's just how to
point it out that's why it is important
for you to understand the general story
in the market so what do we have again
we have another break of structure to
the downside
here let me zoom out so we have another
break of structure to the downside you
know leaving out this particular origin
but here now price did not come into
this origin but look at where it tapped
into just around this level after this
consolidation here just around this
level although it didn't even tap into
the consolidation it reacted off the
imbalance very close to it and pushed
down so we are still um
bearish you know pushing down then we
have this level
two another break of structure so this
is just trying to understand the general
story of how price you know was pushing
down you're not just understanding the
story but as you mapping it out you are
getting your point of Interest your
levels where you'll be taking trades
from so when reading the market
structure you need to be very very
observant you need to open your eyes to
view what is actually happening so from
there we have another break of structure
here I know most people may not map this
out as a break of structure but no
matter how tiny it is whether it is Big
Tiny as far as a level has been
cleared just know that there is a break
of
structure so you can also see price came
back into the origin and pushed down for
to dish out a new break of structure so
you can see how price kept on pushing to
the downside that's why I said whenever
you notice that the trend is bearish or
bullish all you just need to be doing is
just sell currently we are looking at a
bearish structure so all you just need
to do is to sell sell sell you obviously
see when to change Byers to start buying
I still show you guys that so just keep
watching so we have another break of
structure to the downside and you can
see what happened price came back into
the origin so what you just need to be
looking out for is once once you point
out a break of structure wait for the
wait for price to get back into the
origin you sell again it's just that
simple so you can also see we have
another break of structure here so this
is actually the origin but you can see
price kept on pushing to the
downside kept on pushing to the downside
without tapping into the that particular
origin then from here we got the last
break of structure to the downside
because you can see price started
pushing up so let me show you how you
can actually change Trend you can see
where we started from from here we've
been selling selling selling selling and
now
we have the last break of structure here
to the downside so now look at what
happened as price cleared this structure
to the downside this is actually the
origin and what happened price tapped
into that particular origin but if the
bearish trend was meant to continue it
would have given a new break of
structure to the downside and you know
the drill will keep selling to the
downside so what happened price ta
reacted of that origin ditched out a
little cell but from there we got a
change of character so just know that
whenever um there is a shift in Market
um structure let me clone this change of
character here so whenever there is a
shift from the general character of the
market to another you know character
trying to like make it very simple for
you guys so that's why I'm just giving a
literal meaning of it so you can see the
general Trend was actually Market
breaking structure to the downside and
now we've gotten a shift Market is now
breaking structure to the upside so as
price cleared out the last origin that
caused the break of structure to the
downside that indicates a change of
character which is this level that will
indicate what a change of character from
that level and now from this change of
character this is the origin that caused
the change of character but you can see
Market did not get back into the origin
it left it un mitigated and then from
there we started getting break of
structure let me clone our break of
structure
here from there we started getting break
of structure to the upside so what will
you as a Trader change your buyers from
selling to buying gu at this point now
because we have changed Trend so a break
of structure Market tapped into the
origin we have another break of
structure here we have another let me
just we have another break of structure
here and what
happened price tapped into the origin
here and we're still pushing to the
upside
so what did we get here again another
break of structure to the upside okay
this is not a clean break of structure
it just created an equal High there
given a resistant level so whenever
price fails to
Break um an equal High remember guys
we've switched from bearish strength to
bullish Trend now so we are looking at a
bullish Trend so whenever price fails to
break a particular level whether it is a
break of structure to the upside or a
break of structure to the downside
whenever price or the market fails to
break a particular level and creates a
qu High it may indicate that um there
may be a possible change of character
because if the trend is strong we we
should have gotten you know a break of
strcture to the upside so that we'll
continue buying but now we got an equal
High here indicating that a resistant
level has been created here so we can
see from there price you know triggered
you know pushed to the downside a little
but the buyers were still intact so they
it reacted off now this particular
origin now did not create a new break of
structure so we're going to treat it as
a support
level which price tapped into and from
there we got um a break of structure
clearing out this particular um
resistance here so we now have a new
break of structure let me clone this we
have a new break of structure around
this
level a new break of structure now this
being the
origin this is the origin here I guess
price did not mitigate it so we're just
going to leave it pending and from there
we continue pushing to the upside so
let's keep mapping out the break of
structure from here so you can
see after this particular of structure
we got a new one around this
level break of
structure around this
level and then what happened price
tapped into the origin that caused the
break of structure to push
up you know creating a tiny break of
structure here so this is why I said
when reading the market structure you
need to be very observant all these
levels if you are taking entries from
the daily time frame you would have just
been taking an aggressive entry from
here but if you're taking entries from
different um time frames like me now I
take my entries for 15 minutes so once
price Taps into all these Origins all I
do is Rush down to my 15 minutes time
frame and then take my entries so you
understand what I mean if you have seen
my video on Entry
strategy so we have um another break of
structure
here and what happened price tapped into
the origin let me put this one pending
here so price tapped into the origin
although it extend a extended a little
bit here but
now uh we have another break of
structure
here we have another break of structure
here so you can see how I'm pointing
everything out and then from this break
of structure this is actually the origin
that caused the break of structure all
these things were more like
consolidation but now I'm refining it to
the last Candlestick before the posive
movement that caused this particular
break of structure and you can see price
stopped in dishing out a break of
structure as Market is clearing out all
these resistance levels because you I
will upload a video also explaining how
to point out a valid break structure so
stay tuned guys so as Market is clearing
out all these resistant levels it's
indicating that we are bullish so like I
stated just keep buying until we see
another res
to change Byers which has happened from
from
here as price cleared this particular
structure to the upside what
happened this is the origin that caused
the break of structure to the upside and
you can see how price reacted but from
there we got a push to the downside
indicating a change of character
indicating a change of character let's
clone this our friend here there change
of character
so indicating a change of character
around this level so that's Implement
price has changed direction from pushing
up to pushing down and you can see
inside there we were just getting break
of structure but price was not tapping
into the OR
regions that
caus the you know break of structure
because we have this price didn't come
back it just re of imbalance you know
pushed although imbalance is also a
level where you can take your entries
from but preferably for me I just love
taking from my other blocks so I can see
price kept on breaking Str to the
downside and then what happened here so
if you let me zoom in so that everyone
can see so if you check from this level
we got another
break to the downside around on this
level and price came into the origin but
it didn't push down further instead we
got a change of character around this
level change of
character so that implements this
bearish trend that just started um we
have the buyers again coming in change
of character and then price tapped into
the origin that caused the change of
character we started pushing
up again breaking structures to the
upside just like we have it here
breaking structure to the upside and
what happened as we've gotten this break
of structure price tapped into the
origin that caused the break of
structure another break of structure
here and this is
actually the origin that caused the
break of structure but you can see
Market didn't come back into the origin
so it left it up mitigated instead it to
push to the upside we have another break
of structure
here and what happened price tapped into
the origin pushed up again another break
of structure is present
here and price also tapped into the
origin and pushed up giving us a new
break of structure we are fully um
bullish just keep buying as we are still
breaking structures to the upside just
keep buying that is it so from here
price kept on ranging for a while you
can see how it was giving a sideways
movement here so remember the
illustration I gave about sideways
movement so let me just put it from here
so it was giving a sideways movement
inside here you can see push up equal
highs and you know just dancing around
this particular box here until what
happened we got another break to the
upside so if you were actually buying
and price started ranging at least you
should have taken your profit around
this level because this range um showed
that um uh the market was trying to get
a new Direction whether it will break to
the downside or it will keep pushing up
so as we got a break to the
upside it indicated that we are still
bullish so what will it do still wait
for price to tap into the origin that
cost the break of structure here you can
see what happened mapping out the origin
that cost the break of structure price
tapped in pushed up a little bit from
here but it didn't give us a new break
of structure instead we got a break to
the downside indicating that we have a
change change of
character around this
level that is a change of character
around this level here and from there
price was still you know breaking
structure to the downside so this is
actually the last break of structure
here to the downside
us that is the last break of structure
here to the downside and what
happened this is the origin but when
price got into that particular origin
um instead of reacting and pushing to
the downside it it dished out a
new um break to the upside indicating
that the trend has changed so that
simply means the buyers are still in
because we've gotten a change of cor the
sellers just came in pushed the market
down a little bit but the buyers are
still in so now we have
this change of character from here price
tapped into the origin that caused the
change of character and we started
getting a new break of structure to the
upside we have this this a break of
structure to the upside and price kept
on pushing up and now we have a clear
break here this break of structure I
know Market did not come back into the
region instead reacted of this imbalance
here so now we have a new break of
structure around this level and you can
see how price is currently reacting at
the
origin you know price tapped into the
origin remember I said the market is
closed as I'm shooting this particular
video so you can see where we started
reading the structure understanding the
story everything that is going on up
until this level now so you can see we
have the most recent break of structure
and um last week we've just been buying
more of gu because we are bullish
getting this break of structure we've
been buying gu and you can see this or
that caused this record structure is
dishing out another push to the upside
so if the buyers are still strong in the
market they will break this particular
level give us a new break of structure
you know the drill we wait for the
origin that costed and we keep pushing
up so that is
actually the importance of reading the
Market structure you understand
everything that is going on and know
when to take your entries you know what
is going on you know whether there are
more buyers or there are more sellers in
the market so guys following our
strategy remember I stated that I will
show you guys um the best structures
that works with our strategy so
following our strategy whenever the
market has a direction that is um the
best time to apply our strategy so if
the market is pushing to the upside just
be looking out for buys and then if the
market is pushing to the downside just
be looking out for sells well if the
market is ranging just like we around
here if the market is ranging you know
consolidating just stay out until there
is a direction because if the market is
ranging you won't be able to point out a
break of structure and then the origion
because when the market is ranging there
is no break of structure at all so that
implements our strategy will not work
when the market is ranging wait until
there's a d Direction then you start
taking your entries mapping out your
Origins you know getting your buyers and
the rest so you can see clearly that's
what we have here from the daily time
frame now you can see like I said price
has rected of this origin and it's
pushing up so this buy if I go down to
my entry time frame I all I will just be
doing there is to be looking out for buy
setups buy setups and I'll be buying
having this level in mind too because if
price should get here this is a
resistant level it can still react I can
only keep buying if price should come
here and still clear to the upside and
then I can change buers to start selling
if I see a change of character just like
we got here change of character a change
of character you can see where we
started from a bearish trend from a
bearish trend we switched to bullish
from bullish bearish again bullish so
just like that you get to understand the
full story everything that scre on the
chat and from there you will get your
Biers it's just that simple that's why I
said it is very important for you to
know how to read the market structure as
a Trader so guys remember feel free to
message me with your setups you can read
the market structure and send it to me
to check if you are actually getting it
if you actually got you know all my
explanations here
um all my explanations here so all you
just need to do just send in your setup
um following our strategy too because I
get a lot of persons you know sending in
their setups for me whether you're in my
VIP group or whether in my free group
just feel free I'll dropped the link in
the comments so just feel free to send
your setups send read the market
structure and send in then I will view
if there's any corrections I'll still
help you there all right guys so as
you've seen this video make sure you
practice learn how to map out your
structures just following the steps I
have showed you guys here thanks once
again for watching and don't forget to
like subscribe and turn on notification
Bell so that you get the first to be
notified when I upload a new video don't
forget to share too bye for now